<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Administrivia on COMP52315 – Performance Engineering</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/</link><description>Recent content in Administrivia on COMP52315 – Performance Engineering</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Contact details</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/contact/</guid><description>Lecturer contact details # The course is taught by Lawrence Mitchell, the best way to get in touch is via email lawrence.mitchell@durham.ac.uk.
The course materials are also hosted on GitHub, so if you find mistakes in them please let me know there.</description></item><item><title>Hamilton accounts</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/hamilton/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/hamilton/</guid><description>Access to Hamilton # For many of the exercises in the course, we will be using the Hamilton supercomputer. You should have already obtained an account on Hamilton as part of Core Ib. If you do not yet have one, please register following their instructions.
Since we&amp;rsquo;ll be logging in a lot, I also provide some tips on how to configure ssh for swifter login.
Quickstart reminder # If you want to remind yourself of how Hamilton works, take a look at the quickstart guide from PHYS52105.</description></item><item><title>ssh configuration</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/configuration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/configuration/</guid><description>ssh tips &amp;amp; tricks # Setting up simpler logins # It can be tedious to remember to type long login commands every time when logging in via ssh to hamilton. I therefore recommend that you set up an ssh config file.
Additionally, you might also want to set up ssh keys for passwordless login.
The ssh-config configuration file # Mac/Linux When you run ssh it reads a configuration file at $HOME/.</description></item><item><title>Unix resources</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/unix/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/comp52315/setup/unix/</guid><description>Using Unix-like systems for computational science # This course presupposes some level of familiarity with commandline interfaces. You have encountered these already in the previous term. In case you need a quick refresher, I recommend the material produced by the Software Carpentry project.
They have a number of useful lessons and materials providing introductory training on how to do things like use the Unix shell, version control with git, and some introductory programming and plotting in Python.</description></item></channel></rss>